Guide to the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Program Interviews SC0932
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Faculty and Staff Interviews, 2007-2016; Series 5
  - Gelpi, Albert Joseph., 2013 Feb 14-Mar 7
    Albert Joseph Gelpi was born on July 19, 1931 in New Orleans, where he attended Jesuit High School and got his A. B. from Loyola University, New Orleans. After serving in the U. S. Army (1951-53, the last year in Korea), he got his M. A. from Tulane and taught briefly at Loyola before starting doctoral studies at Harvard in fall, 1957. He received his PhD from Harvard in 1962 with a dissertation on Emily Dickinson under the supervision of Perry Miller. While teaching there as an assistant professor for the next six years, he married Barbara Charlesworth in 1965, and they had two children: Christopher (b. 1966) and Adrienne (b. 1970). In 1965 his dissertation was published by Harvard University Press under the title Emily Dickinson: The Mind of the Poet.
    In the fall of 1968 the Gelpis came to Stanford with Albert as a tenured associate professor and Barbara as a lecturer. During the thirty-plus years on the Stanford teaching faculty, Gelpi offered a range of courses in American literature on the undergraduate and graduate levels, earning him a Dean’s Teaching Award shortly before his full retirement in 2002. He was Guggenheim Fellow, 1977-78, and became the William Robertson Coe Professor of American Literature in 1979. Besides teaching, Gelpi served in a number of administrative post within the department, including Chair (1985-88), and in the University, including several stints as Chair of the American Studies Program (1976-77, 1989-90, 1994-7), and as Associate Dean of Graduate Studies and Research (1980-85). He was the founding editor of the influential monograph series “Cambridge Studies in American Literature and Culture,” published by Cambridge University Press, and served in that capacity from 1980 to 1991.
    Gelpi’s primary field of scholarly and critical interest is American poetry, and, in addition to many journal articles and essays in collections, he has written, besides the Dickinson book, a three volume study of the development of an American poetic tradition from the Puritans through the twentieth century: The Tenth Muse: The Psyche of the American Poet (1975, reissued, 1991); A Coherent Splendor: The American Poetic Renaissance 1910-1950 (1987); and American Poetry After Modernism: The Power of the Word ( forthcoming, 2015).
    He has also edited a number of important books in the field of American poetry: The Poet in America 1650 to the Present (1973); (with Barbara Charlesworth Gelpi) Adrienne Rich’s Poetry (1973) and Adrienne Rich’s Poetry and Prose (1992); Wallace Stevens: The Poetics of Modernism (1986); Denise Levertov: Selected Criticism (1993); The Blood of the Poet: Selected Poems of William Everson (1994); (with Jacqueline Brogan) A Whole New Poetry Beginning Here: Adrienne Rich in the Eighties & Nineties (1998); The Wild God of the World: An Anthology of Robinson Jeffers (2003); Dark God of Eros: A William Everson Reader (2003), and (with Robert Bertholf) The Letters of Robert Duncan & Denise Levertov (2003), which won an award from the Modern Language Association in 2004 as the best scholarly edition.
    In 1993 he published Living in Time: The Poetry of C. Day-Lewis, and is planning, with Bernard O’Donoghue, a Selected Prose of C. Day-Lewis.
    Gelpi continues to teach from time to time in Stanford Continuing Studies and in its Master of Liberal Arts Program.
  - Gelpi, Barbara C., 2013 Feb 12-Mar 12
    Barbara Charlesworth Gelpi begins her interview discussing her early life in Colombia, her parents and her sister, her education in catholic schools in Colombia and Toronto, Canada, as well as her undergraduate and graduate work at the University of Miami. Gelpi goes on to discuss her doctoral work at Radcliffe and meeting Albert Gelpi. She notes her positions at University of California, Santa Barbara, Brandies, and marrying Albert, who accepted a position in 1967 at Stanford. Gelpi discusses the unrest on campus at the time and her experience as a woman and a lecturer in Stanford’s English Department. Gelpi notes the difficulty she faced getting a regular appointment at Stanford, and her experience at San Jose State. She recounts her work with other female faculty in developing interdisciplinary courses and texts dealing with women, and the founding of the Center for Research on Women (CROW).
    Gelpi opens the second session discussing at length her experience as editor of Signs, including its influence and reception. She also discusses other Stanford faculty and staff who assisted with Signs and the challenges they all faced in editing the journal. Gelpi further explores her experience as a woman and a spouse of a faculty member in the English Department, and how she dealt with changing societal norms. She recounts her efforts to get a tenure track position and eventually tenure within the department. She concludes by discussing her time as interim director at the Clayman Institute and thoughts on Stanford’s evolution since her arrival.
    Barbara Charlesworth was born of Canadian parents in a Colombian oil camp named El Centro. She had her primary education in the one-room schoolhouse there and spent her middle and high school years at Loretto Abbey, Toronto. After receiving a summa cum laude B.A. (1955) and an M.A. (1957) in English from the University of Miami, Charlesworth entered Radcliffe College in 1957. (At that time, both the undergraduate and the graduate women students at Radcliffe took all their courses at Harvard and fulfilled all of Harvard’s requirements but still were awarded a Radcliffe, not a Harvard, degree.) When she received her Ph.D. in 1962, her dissertation, entitled Dark Passages: The Decadent Consciousness in Victorian Literature, received the Howard Mumford Jones award as the year’s best in the fields of British and American Literature and was published in 1965 by the Wisconsin University Press.
    After two years (1962-64) as an assistant professor at the University of California, Santa Barbara, Charlesworth returned east in 1964 to join the faculty at Brandeis. She married Albert Gelpi, then an assistant professor at Harvard, in 1965. Two years later, after the birth in 1966 of the Gelpis’ first child, Christopher, Gelpi resigned her Brandeis position, and when Albert Gelpi accepted a tenured post at Stanford in 1968, she also joined the department as a part-time lecturer. The couple’s second child, Adrienne, was born in 1970.
    Beginning in the early 1970s Gelpi was in the vanguard of the burgeoning field of feminist literary criticism. With Albert Gelpi she edited Adrienne Rich’s Poetry, published by W.W. Norton in 1975, and in 1977 was one of an interdisciplinary group which studied the life cycle of Victorian women, work that culminated in Victorian Women: A Documentary Account of Women’s Lives in Nineteenth Century England, France, and the United States, published by the Stanford University Press in 1981. Meanwhile, in 1980 when the University of Chicago Press chose Stanford’s newly established Center for Research on Women (CROW) to house Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society, Gelpi, with an interdisciplinary team of Stanford associates, became its editor, a post she held until 1985.
    Gelpi, who had continued in her part-time lectureship in English through these years, joined the English Department as a half-time untenured associate professor in 1982, and became a tenured professor in 1992, the same year that she published Shelley’s Goddess: Maternity, Language, Subjectivity with Oxford University Press. She won the Lillian and Thomas B. Rhodes Award for excellence in undergraduate teaching in 1993. As chair of the department’s technology committee she was one of the pioneers in bringing technology into liberal arts class rooms and in 1996 was given a Bing Technology Grant for graduate student training. In 2002-4 she served as Acting Director of the Institute for Research on Women and Gender and then retired from Stanford. Her recent scholarship centers on the Oxford Movement in nineteenth-century England.
  - Gibbons, James F., 2009 Jan 28
    In his first interview, James Gibbons talked about his impressions of Stanford since arriving in 1953; the turbulence on campus in the late 1960s and the erosion of trust between faculty & students; creative problem solving and stories about Bill Shockley, his idea of teaching as coaching and seeing things differently. He also discussed fundamental physics research versus engineering development of advanced technology, the move of the Computer Science Department from the School of Humanities and Sciences, Don Knuth, and the major role of the School of Engineering in almost all Stanford academic & industrial partnerships.
    In his second interview, James Gibbons discussed SERA Solar Cell Corporation and the background of solar cell research, his research into silicon films and new photovoltaic technology, the value of connections to the semiconductor industry, the importance of Stanford University as an entrepreneurial place, and Tutored Video Instruction (TVI).
    In his third interview, James Gibbons discussed TVI further, its valuable uses beyond Stanford and comparison to the new approach of “massively open online courses.” Gibbons also gave his advice to today’s students and discussed multidisciplinary research, the successes of two-party collaborations, the Center for Integrated Systems (CIS), and fundraising. He reflected on John Linvill, past Stanford presidents, and his endeavors as the Dean of Engineering.
    Professor Gibbons received a BS degree at Northwestern University in 1953 and a PhD from Stanford in 1956. He joined the Stanford faculty in 1957, was appointed professor of electrical engineering in 1964, and dean of the School of Engineering in 1984. In 1983 he was named Reid Weaver Dennis Professor of Electrical Engineering, and in 1984 the Frederick Emmons Terman Dean of the School of Engineering. He served as Dean from September 1984 to June 1996.
    His principal research interests are in the fields of semiconductor device analysis, process physics and technology and solar energy. He is the author of four textbooks in semiconductor electronics, four research monographs in the fields of ion implantation and beam processing of semiconductors and over 250 papers. He received the IEEE Jack A. Morton Award (1980), the Texas Instruments Founder's Prize (1982), the Semiconductor Industry Association's University Research Award (1996), and the American Electronics Association Medal of Achievement (1996) for his pioneering research in the use of ion implantation and rapid thermal processing techniques for solid-state physics and technology.
    In 1972, he invented the Tutored Video Instruction process, which he and his colleagues at Stanford and Hewlett-Packard developed into a highly regarded model for video-based distance learning, first used for the in-plant education of engineers in industry. He was awarded the IEEE Medal of Education (1981) for this work and for his semiconductor texts. Upon leaving the dean's office in 1996, Gibbons founded SERA Learning Technologies, a company devoted to using tutored video instruction for the education of at risk and underserved youth.
    As dean, he created several important interschool programs with the School of Humanities and Sciences, the Graduate School of Business and the School of Medicine. In 1986, he brought the computer science department into the School of Engineering and initiated the thorough integration of that discipline into the departments and research centers of the School, an activity that has been continued and amplified by his successors. He also engaged venture capitalists in helping to build the school's endowment, through the Engineering Venture Fund, and to create new educational opportunities for students through the Technology Ventures Program.
    Starting in 1985, he worked with the President and a group of senior colleagues in the university administration to create a plan for the Science and Engineering Quad, and he contributed to its implementation by raising naming gifts and supporting funds for several buildings in the SEQ. Within the school, he worked with the department chairs to put in place new standards for tenure that included high quality in both teaching and research, leading to a new plateau in the national ranking of the school. Upon his retirement from the office of dean, the University named a grove of trees outside the Thornton Center for him. A marker in that grove carries the inscription: "His enormous contributions as teacher, scholar, entrepreneur and dean have changed forever the physical and intellectual landscape of Stanford and the School of Engineering. His visionary leadership has set us on a course of unparalleled excellence and ensured the preeminence of our endeavors for generations to come."
    Professor Gibbons is a member of the National Academy of Engineering, the National Academy of Sciences, a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and a Lifetime Fellow of the IEEE. He was named an Outstanding Alumnus of Northwestern University in 1987 and was awarded the IEEE Millennium Medal in 2001.
  - Gibbs, James Lowell, 2015-10-27
    In this 2015 oral history interview, anthropologist James Lowell Gibbs Jr. discusses his early life and education, his fieldwork in Liberia, teaching anthropology to undergraduates, and his service as Stanford University’s first dean of undergraduate studies.
    Gibbs describes his family background and credits the book African Journey by Eslanda Goode Robeson with sparking his interest in anthropology. He discusses his undergraduate education at Cornell University, especially conducting social science research on intergroup relations as an undergraduate--an experience that would later inform his ideas about undergraduate education as a Stanford administrator. He speaks of the Rotary Foundation Fellowship that allowed him to study anthropology at Cambridge for a year and discusses his graduate education at Harvard, where he learned from Cora Du Bois and others.
    Shifting to his research, Gibbs describes the circumstances that led him to focus on tribal law among the Kpelle people of Liberia and relates memories of his field work there, including the making of the prize-winning film, The Cows of Dolo Kenpaye.
    Gibbs recounts his rationale for moving from the University of Minnesota to Stanford in 1966. He describes the founding of the Program in African and Afro-American Studies and the recruitment of St. Clair Drake to direct the program. He recalls some of the work that he did as Stanford’s first dean of undergraduate studies, and he discusses his tenure a chair of the Department of Anthropology and the split of the department that occurred in the late 1990s.
    Gibbs also discusses his efforts to recruit minority faculty and his work with student-initiated programs such as SWOPSI (Student Workshop on Political and Social Improvement) and SCIRE (Student Center for Innovation in Research and Education). He concludes by commenting on vivid Stanford memories and some of the board positions he has held.
  - Gilly, William F., 2016-02-22
    William Gilly is a biology professor at Stanford’s Hopkins Marine Station whose research has contributed to our basic understanding of electrical excitability in nerve and muscle cells in a wide variety of organisms ranging from brittle stars to mammals. In this interview, Gilly discusses the path his science career has taken, including measuring gas diffusion across membranes, patch clamping giant squid neurons, and retracing John Steinbeck and Edward Ricketts’s expedition to the Sea of Cortez. Beyond his research, he explains how he has incorporated exploration and discovery into his courses and science outreach.
    Gilly begins the interview with his affinity for Uncle Wiggly, an aged but adventurous rabbit from a series of children’s stories, and describes his own independent forays into the natural surroundings of Allentown, Pennsylvania when he was a child. He explains his family’s technical background and how his interest in ham radio led him to pursue an electrical engineering degree at Princeton.
    Gilly details the independent undergraduate research project that landed him in a neurophysiology lab, shifted his focus to biology, and, despite inconclusive results, earned him an award from his engineering department. He describes his acceptance to the PhD program at Washington University in St. Louis and how, when his advisor died suddenly, a network of friends and acquaintances from Yale University, the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole, and the University of Washington’s Friday Harbor Laboratories enabled him to complete his research and thesis in physiology and biophysics and to begin a postdoctoral fellowship in Clara Franzini-Armstrong’s lab at the University of Pennsylvania, studying the role of ion channels in electrical signaling in squid axons.
    This expertise, Gilly explains, resulted in his appointment at Stanford, working at Hopkins Marine Station where he could collect squid specimens directly from the bay. Citing his experiences both as a scientist and fisherman, he opines on the ways that the Monterey Bay has and has not recovered. After discussing the bureaucratic challenges of achieving tenure, he launches into stories about the classes he has taught, including a technical training course on patch clamping squid neurons, a holistic biology class that involved field research in Baja California Big Sur and the Salinas River, and the Steinbeck Summer Institutes program for primary educators.
    A central text to many of these courses is Steinbeck and Ricketts’s Sea of Cortez: A Leisurely Journal of Travel and Research, and Gilly discusses how he and several colleagues organized their own expedition based on Steinbeck and Ricketts’s sea voyage. He details preparations and sponsorship for the trip and mentions how the original expedition’s ship, the Western Flyer, is being restored for outreach and possible future trips.
    Gilly talks about his other outreach work, including donating giant squid to primary classrooms for his Squid4Kids program, trying to mount a critter-cam on a squid for National Geographic TV, and serving as a National Geographic Expert on their Lindblad cruises in the Sea of Cortez. He concludes the interview by discussing his current project helping to set up a community-run marine lab in Santa Rosalía, Baja California Sur, Mexico and how it might be used for environmental research and education.
  - Greenberg, Harry B., 2015-09-21
    Harry B. Greenberg, MD, the Joseph D. Grant Professor in the School of Medicine and Senior Associate Dean for Research, was the lead inventor of the first-generation vaccine for rotavirus, a severe diarrheal disease that kills between 300,000 and 400,000 children each year in the developing world. In this interview, he discusses a range of important topics including developments in virology from 1970 to 2015 with a specific focus on vaccines for rotavirus and influenza, the relationship between the research and clinical sides of the Stanford School of Medicine in the late-twentieth century, the effects of entrepreneurism on medical research, ethical issues in medical research and Stanford’s responses to them, as well as the growth of the school from 1983 to 2015.
  - Growing Pains of Physics at Stanford, 2011
  - Guertin, Richard and Kiefer, William C., 2010 Jun 4
  - Hamburg, David A., 2012 Feb 14-Nov 20
    In this multi-part oral history, David A. Hamburg told much of his life story, beginning with his family background. The first interview included stories of his family background and the educational experiences of his father, as well as his own. He then went on to tell a little about his military training and service during WWII, followed by a move to medical practice and research after his service ended. This interview also covered his life in Chicago, involvement with NIMH, and the move to Stanford. The second interview continued with descriptions of the research done at Stanford and the research culture, the development of the Human Biology Department, the evolution of the Psychiatry Department, and NIH intramural programs. Hamburg also described his friendship with Wallace Sterling, his participation in Stanford leadership and campus service, and the protests of the 1960s and 1970s. This interview concluded with a preliminary look at the Primate Research Lab.
    Parts three and four of the interviews focused mostly on Stanford’s Primate Research Lab on campus and the research stations in Africa. Hamburg also offered his take on Jane Goodall, and described the Gombe Stream Kidnapping in detail. The final interview explained why Hamburg left Stanford in 1975. In the conversation, Hamburg also spoke of his work on the Stanford Board of Trustees, his role in the selection of President Richard W. Lyman, and his take on the Donald Kennedy presidency. Finally, he spoke about his participation in Board of Trustees committees and the establishment of the Cancer Institute on campus.
    David A. Hamburg is Visiting Scholar at the American Association for the Advancement of Science and DeWitt Wallace Distinguished Scholar at Weill Cornell Medical College. He is President Emeritus at Carnegie Corporation of New York. Hamburg has a long history of leadership in biological and behavioral sciences. He has been a pioneer in prevention of mass violence. He has been a professor at Stanford University and Harvard University, President of the Institute of Medicine, National Academy of Sciences, and President of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
    He was a member of the United States Defense Policy Board with Secretary of Defense William Perry and co-chair with former Secretary of State Cyrus Vance of the Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict. The Commission published many books and monographs in its five-year life (1994-99), covering diplomatic, political, economic and military aspects of prevention.
    He was a member of President Clinton’s Committee of Advisors on Science and Technology. He chaired committees at the United Nations and European Union on the prevention of genocide.
    He is the author of Today’s Children: Creating a Future for a Generation in Crisis (1992); No More Killing Fields: Preventing Deadly Conflict (2002); and Learning to Live Together: Preventing Hatred and Violence in Child and Adolescent Development (2004); and Preventing Genocide: Practical Steps toward Early Detection and Effective Action (2008). An educational documentary was based on the book. His new book is Give Peace a Chance: Preventing Mass Violence (2013). In 2012, the Foreign Policy Association established the Andrew Carnegie Distinguished Lecture in Honor of David Hamburg on an annual basis.
    Dr. Hamburg has received numerous awards including the Foreign Policy Association’s Medal; the Sarnat International Mental Health Award of the Institute of Medicine, National Academy of Sciences; the John Stearns Medal for Lifetime Achievement in Medicine, New York Academy of Medicine; Leadership in Violence Prevention, United States Institute of Peace; George Brown Award for International Scientific Cooperation, CRDF Global; the National Academy of Sciences Public Welfare Medal (its highest award); and the Presidential Medal of Freedom (the highest civilian award of the United States).
  - Hamrdla, G. Robert, 2011 Feb 25